{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This battle ended an invasion whose leader, seeking revenge for the Ionian Revolt, had an assistant constantlytellhim“Master,remembertheAthenians.”DatisandArtapherneswerethelosingcommanders at this battle, which frustrated Darius the Great. News of this battle was swiftly delivered to Athens via Pheidippides [fuh-dip-ih-dees], a runner. For ten points, name this Greek victory, commemorated today with a 26 mile run.",
      "answer": "Battle of Marathon"
    },
    {
      "question": "After tackling and beating a man named Wesley, this figure quipped “Sorry I had a fight in the middle of your Black Panther meeting.” After a Viet Cong bombing, this man rescued Lieutenant Dan and Bubba, acting against his girlfriend Jenny’s advice to “run.” The advice “life is like a box of chocolates” is given by the mother of, for ten points, what 1994 film character, played by Tom Hanks, who inexplicably experiences much of 20th century American history?",
      "answer": [
        "Forrest Gump",
        "either",
        "both"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Many holders of this profession, including the Qawasmi, operated in the Trucial States on a coast named for this profession. One holder of this profession, Hayreddin Barbarossa, later became Pasha of Algeria. Stephen Decatur was forced to burn the Philadelphia in the first of several Barbary Wars, which were fought by the United States against North African holders of this profession. For ten points, name this profession, commonly practiced in modern-day Somalia, in which individuals steal valuables from ships.",
      "answer": [
        "piracy",
        "word forms"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Objects undergoing this process were sometimes dried out using the chemical natron or naturally by extreme cold. The byproducts of one stage of this process were often stored in canopic jars decorated with animals like jackals and baboons. Anubis was the god of this technique, which involves a final step of wrapping in linen bandages. For ten points, name this type of embalming that was common for pharaohs of ancient Egypt.",
      "answer": [
        "mummification",
        "descriptions like “creating mummies”"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The losers of this battle were induced into a mass panic known as the Runaway Scrape. During a meeting in this battle, William Travis drew a line in the sand and allowed all who stepped across to leave. Davy Crockett and Jim Bowie were among the 200 defenders of a San Antonio mission who died in this 1836 battle. For ten points, name this victory for the Mexican army, inspiring a Texan call to “remember [this battle].”",
      "answer": "Battle of the Alamo"
    },
    {
      "question": "This figure stands next to Saint Barbara and Saint Sixtus in a Sistine painting by Raphael. When shown with another religious figure on her lap, this figure is known as the “Seat of Wisdom.” Scenes of the Annunciation show the angel Gabriel entering the house of this woman and her husband Joseph. For ten points, name this religious figure, known in Italian art as Madonna, and often shown holding her son, Jesus Christ.",
      "answer": [
        "the Virgin Mary",
        "either",
        "both",
        "Madonna before mentioned,"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This president affirmed the right to intervene in South American relations in his namesake corollary and sent the Great White Fleet around the world to showcase American naval power. This man, who claimed to “speak softly and carry a big stick,” broke with William Taft, and ran in the election of 1912 with the Bull Moose party. For ten points, name this early 20th century president who appears with Lincoln, Jefferson, and Washington on Mount Rushmore.",
      "answer": [
        "Theodore Roosevelt",
        "Teddy Roosevelt"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1995, this organization’s LEAR created the nine atoms of anti-hydrogen, the first true antimatter. This group’s AWAKE plasma experiment uses equipment and space once dedicated to the “Neutrinos to Gran Sasso” project. In 2012, scientists with this organization announced experimental data suggesting the finding of the Higgs boson. For ten points, name this research organization, based near Geneva, that operates the Large Hadron Collier.",
      "answer": [
        "CERN or the European Organization for Nuclear Research",
        "the Organisation europ´een pour la Recherche Nucl´eaire"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During this battle, Davy Gam died while leading a band of knights in defense of his monarch. This battle was preceded by a lengthy siege of Harfleur. During this battle, the English used stakes to protect their archers from opposing cavalry and used longbows to devastating effect as the French cavalry trudged through a muddy battlefield. For ten points, name this victory for Henry V during the Hundred Years’ War.",
      "answer": "Battle of Agincourt"
    },
    {
      "question": "This speech presents a metaphor between an island of poverty and an ocean of prosperity and claims that the government’s promissory note has been returned with an “insufficient funds” stamp. This speech’s final section begins by claiming that freedom should ring through every valley and every hamlet and closes with the repeated declaration “Free at last!” For ten points, name this 1963 speech delivered during the March on Washington by Martin Luther King.",
      "answer": "I Have a Dream speech"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country lost a rubber-producing territory to its northern neighbor with the Treaty of Petropolis. This country’s highest point is the extinct volcano Nevado Sajama. This former owner of the State of Acre was the site of a Spanish colonial mint near the silver mines of Potosi, and it lost much of the Gran Chaco in a war with Paraguay. For ten points, name this “plurinational” country in South America that shares Lake Titicaca with Peru and whose two capitals are Sucre and La Paz.",
        "answer": "Plurinational State of Bolivia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Bolivia lost its coastline, including the port city of Antofagasta, to Chile in what conflict, named for a body of water?",
        "answer": [
          "Pacific Ocean",
          "War of the Pacific"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In a Burmese Buddhist ceremony called yay zet cha, this resource is slowly dropped into a vase or other jar. This resource was collected at Srah Srang, one of many large, rectangular barays built by the Khmer empire. The movement of this resource reverses in the Tonl´e Sap after the annual monsoon ends. For ten points, name this resource, provided to millions in Southeast Asia by the Mekong River for irrigation of rice paddies.",
        "answer": "water"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The aforementioned Khmer empire was based in what is now this modern country, where the Khmer Rouge held power in the 20th century.",
        "answer": "Cambodia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During one campaign, this man was criticized for owing a six-figure debt to Tiffany’s. With Dick Armey, this man proposed a set of legislation that included the “Taking Back Our Streets” Act and the “American Dream Restoration” Act; that legislation is often credited with fueling the Republican Revolution of 1994. For ten points, name this politician from Georgia who failed to win the Republican nomination for President in 2012 and served as Speaker of the House from 1995 to 1999.",
        "answer": "Newt Gingrich"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Gingrich’s promised platform for the Republican-majority Congress after the 1994 elections was given this three word name.",
        "answer": "Contract With America"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This author rebutted The Prince chapter-by-chapter in his Anti-Machiavel. He formed a league of princes known as the Fu¨rstenbund to protect Bavarian independence. This man signed the Convention of Westminister with Great Britain as part of the Diplomatic Revolution, and he entertained C.P.E. Bach and Voltaire at his palace of Sanssouci. For ten points, name this enlightened despot who ruled Prussia during the Seven Years War.",
        "answer": "Frederick the Great or Frederick II of Prussia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Frederick the Great partitioned this European county with his Austrian and Russian neighbors, one of three partitions it suffered.",
        "answer": "Poland-Lithuania"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This route was first conceived of in 1921 as a “project in regional planning” by Benton MacKaye. Its original route was completed near Mount Sugarloaf by the Civilian Conservation Corps in 1937, and the highest point of this route is Clingman’s Dome in the Great Smoky Mountains. This route runs over 2,000 miles from Springer Mountain in the south to Mount Katahdin in Maine. For ten points, name this long-distance hiking path from Georgia to Maine that follows a namesake mountain range.",
        "answer": "Appalachian National Scenic Trail"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The midpoint of the Appalachian Trail is usually considered to be this city, now in West Virginia. Its armory was raided by anti-slavery activists in 1859.",
        "answer": "Harpers Ferry"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Marxist thought holds that this process creates a “reserve army.” Murray Rothbard suggested that social pressures make it difficult for wages to fall to a level that would completely eliminate this phenomenon. NAIRU models its “natural rate,” and it exists in structural, frictional, and seasonal types. Stagflation involves a counter-intuitive combination of this phenomenon and inflation. For ten points, name this economic phenomenon representing the number of people in the workforce who are unable to find jobs.",
        "answer": [
          "unemployment",
          "unemployment rate",
          "other elaborations"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A period of American stagflation in the 1970s was triggered, in part, by this man’s “shocking” series of economic actions, including a 90-day freeze on wages and prices and the closing of the “gold window,” breaking the Bretton Woods system.",
        "answer": [
          "Richard Nixon",
          "Nixon shock"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This figure provided the advice to travel through what are now called the Gibbons and Bozeman Passes; that advice was given to colleagues met at Fort Mandan. As a child, this sister of Camheawait was kidnapped by the Hidatsa, from whom she was purchased by Toussaint Charbonneau. This woman was honored in 2000 with the minting of a dollar coin. The Corps of Exploration was aided by, for ten points, what woman, a Shoshone [sho-sho-ne] guide who assisted Lewis and Clark?",
        "answer": "Sacagawea"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Lewis and Clark met Sacagawea and Charbonneau at Fort Mandan, which the Corps built in North Dakota on this river, which they became the first to entirely travel.",
        "answer": "Missouri River"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man defeated an attempted coup by the Anti-Party Group, led by former premier Georgi Malenkov. While serving as a political commissar, this man supported a disastrous attack at Kharkov. This man briefly increased freedoms after denouncing his predecessor’s policies and cult of personality in the Secret Speech. In a speech addressed to Westerners, this ruler claimed that “we will bury you.” For ten points, name this leader of the Soviet Union, the successor of Joseph Stalin.",
        "answer": "Nikita Khrushchev"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1959, Khrushchev informally debated Richard Nixon at the pro-capitalist American National Exhibition in one of these locations, coining the name for the debate.",
        "answer": "Kitchen debate"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Historical Deaths in 2016",
      "prompt": "In addition to all the musicians and actors we lost in 2016, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country where Rama IX [ninth] passed away in Bangkok in October.",
          "answer": "Thailand"
        },
        {
          "question": "American boxer whose arrest for draft evasion during the Vietnam War was overturned by the Supreme Court.",
          "answer": "Muhammad Ali or Cassius Clay"
        },
        {
          "question": "Supreme Court justice whose seat remained vacant for the rest of 2016.",
          "answer": "Antonin Scalia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Astronaut and Ohio senator who became the oldest person in space in 1998.",
          "answer": "John Glenn"
        },
        {
          "question": "Anti-drug activist who served as First Lady from 1981 to 1989.",
          "answer": "Nancy Reagan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nobel Peace Prize winner and Holocaust survivor who wrote Night.",
          "answer": "Elie Wiesel"
        },
        {
          "question": "Former President of Israel who shared in the 1994 Nobel Peace Prize for the Oslo Accords.",
          "answer": "Shimon Peres"
        },
        {
          "question": "Astronomer and advocate for gender equality in the sciences who helped discover dark matter.",
          "answer": "Vera Rubin"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Napoleonic Wars",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country that Napoleon ruled as Emperor.",
          "answer": "France"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that successfully drove out Napoleon after he captured Moscow.",
          "answer": "Russia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Main waterway of western Germany, a river that named a confederation of German states created by Napoleon.",
          "answer": "Rhine River or the Confederation of the Rhine"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where he decisively defeated the Ottomans at the Battle of the Pyramids.",
          "answer": "Ottoman Egypt"
        },
        {
          "question": "Massive force assembled by Napoleon to invade Britain, but which never did; it formed the core of Napoleon’s invasion force in Russia.",
          "answer": "Grande Arm´ee"
        },
        {
          "question": "Royal family restored to power under Louis XVIII [eighteenth] after the Napoleonic Wars.",
          "answer": "House of Bourbon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Foreign isolationist policy developed by Napoleon, forbidding allies from trading with Britain.",
          "answer": "Continental System"
        },
        {
          "question": "Decisive victory for Napoleon against the Third Coalition, after which he signed the Treaty of Pressburg.",
          "answer": "Battle of Austerlitz or the Battle of the Three Emperors"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "OPEC",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Unofficial leader, an Arabian kingdom led from Riyadh that produces over ten million barrels of oil a day.",
          "answer": "Saudi Arabia"
        },
        {
          "question": "South American member with the largest proven oil reserves, once led by Hugo Chavez.",
          "answer": "Venezuela"
        },
        {
          "question": "1980s war between two of its members to control the vital Shatt-al-Arab waterway.",
          "answer": "Iran-Iraq War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Action often taken by OPEC against countries it wishes to punish, a refusal to trade.",
          "answer": "oil embargo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Controversial method of breaking rockbed to access oil and natural gas, causing a recent supply glut that harmed OPEC economies.",
          "answer": "hydraulic fracturing or fracking"
        },
        {
          "question": "OPEC member that suppressed a secessionist movement in its oil-rich region of Biafra in the 1960s.",
          "answer": "Nigeria"
        },
        {
          "question": "OPEC member that uses its wealth to fund the Al Jazeera media network.",
          "answer": "Qatar"
        },
        {
          "question": "Organization that promotes trade and competition, contrasting with OPEC’s mission of collusion amongst members. A 1999 conference of this body in Seattle was strongly protested.",
          "answer": "World Trade Organization"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A senator from this state was killed in a plane crash eleven days before the 2002 election, after which Norm Coleman became the most recent Republican to win a Senate seat from this state. Paul Wellstone served in this state’s (20 pts)",
        "Democratic-Farmer-Labor party, which replaced him on the 2002 ballot with Walter Mondale. Mark Dayton is the current governor of, and (10 pts)",
        "Amy Klobuchar and Al Franken are the current senators from, for ten points, what U.S. state where Coleman had served as mayor of St. Paul?"
      ],
      "answer": "Minnesota"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One of these pieces was premiered with satirical lyrics in the wake of a defeat in the Seven Weeks War. Maurice Ravel imitated Schubert with his “noble” and “sentimental” works of this type. (20 pts)",
        "Chopin wrote a “grande” “brilliante” piece of this type, as well as one inspired by the sight of a dog chasing its own tail, nicknamed (10 pts)",
        "“Minute.” “The Beautiful Blue Danube” is, for ten points, what type of Austrian-born dance in three-four time, often composed by its “king” Johann Strauss II?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "waltz",
        "elaborations using any of the adjectives and titles in quotemarks above"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man raised a levy from the surrounding counties at Egbert’s Stone in order to win the Battle of Ethandun. Much of the information about this man comes from (20 pts)",
        "Bishop Asser. He created a series of fortified positions known as burhs that were required to provide a form of taxes called hides. His defeat of Guthrum allowed him to establish a region known as the Danelaw. Christian principles were added to (10 pts)",
        "Saxon law codes to create the Doom Book during the reign of, for ten points, what King of Wessex, a “Great” Anglo-Saxon king?"
      ],
      "answer": "Alfred the Great or Alfred I of Wessex"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this city, an author hired massive crowds to attend the premiere of his play Hernani to avoid censorship. An 1862 novel contains a lengthy digression on this city’s (20 pts)",
        "sewer system. In two scenes set in this city, Javert [zha-vair] commits suicide by jumping into a river, and Marius is dragged from the (10 pts)",
        "barricades during the 1830 July Revolution by Jean Valjean. Several scenes in Les Mis´erables [lay miz-er-ahb] are set in, for ten points, what capital city of France?"
      ],
      "answer": "Paris"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) At a State of the Union speech, Barack Obama claimed that this case “reversed a century of law.” This case upheld the legality of 60 day buffers and partially overturned a 2002 Supreme Court case involving Mitch (20 pts)",
        "McConnell. This case arose after the plaintiffs were prevented from advertising for Hillary: The Movie by the McCain-Feingold Act. First Amendment protections on free (10 pts)",
        "speech were cited in, for ten points, what 2010 Supreme Court case that struck down certain campaign financing laws?"
      ],
      "answer": "Citizens United vs. Federal Election Commission or FEC"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This group operated the Peterhof base in Novgorod until they were expelled by Ivan III. This group’s defeat of Valdemar IV led to the Treaty of Stralsund, which guaranteed this organization’s control of (20 pts)",
        "Visby. It established trade posts in important cities called kontors, and its members were governed by the Laws of (10 pts)",
        "Lu¨beck, named for its most important town. This organization began as a group of free Imperial cities seeking to control the Baltic fish trade. For ten points, name this medieval trade league in northern Germany."
      ],
      "answer": "Hanseatic League or the Hansa"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader defeated his rival Zwide [zwee-day] at the Battles of Mhlatuze [m’lah-too-zay] River and Gqokli Hill. Henry Francis Fynn was given special access to Natal after treating this man. This ruler’s downfall at the hands of his half-brother (20 pts)",
        "Dingane [din-gah-nay] was assured after he caused a famine in the wake of his mother Nandi’s death. This man’s military accomplishments included the implementation of the (10 pts)",
        "iklwa spears and “buffalo horn” formation. For ten points, name this founder of the Zulu kingdom."
      ],
      "answer": "Shaka Zulu or Shaka kaSenzangakhona"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Part of this territory was placed under Amos Stoddard’s military rule after it was transferred on Three Flags Day. After the discovery of the secret Treaty of (20 pts)",
        "San Ildefonso, John Livingston was sent to purchase part of this territory. The rebellion of Toussaint [too-sahn] Louverture in Haiti, as well as a desire to raise (10 pts)",
        "funds for war against England, prompted Napol´eon to sell this territory for only fifteen million dollars. For ten points, name this large Midwestern territory purchased by the government of Thomas Jefferson in 1803."
      ],
      "answer": "Louisiana Purchase"
    }
  ]
}